<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true Christ owned in a few plain words of truth, by way of reply to all such professors or profane who lay to the charge the elect people of God called Quakers that they deny the bloud of Christ, and his body, and resurrection, and that they deny the Lord that brought them, and trample the blood of the Covenant under their feet ... / by William Bayly.</title>
            <author>Bayly, William, d. 1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1667</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27139</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1542</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25915</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09288463</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09288463</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42619</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27139)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42619)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1301:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true Christ owned in a few plain words of truth, by way of reply to all such professors or profane who lay to the charge the elect people of God called Quakers that they deny the bloud of Christ, and his body, and resurrection, and that they deny the Lord that brought them, and trample the blood of the Covenant under their feet ... / by William Bayly.</title>
                  <author>Bayly, William, d. 1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>23 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1667.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42619:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE True Chriſt Ovvned, IN A few <hi>Plain Words</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> by way of <hi>Reply</hi> to all ſuch <hi>Profeſſors</hi> or <hi>Profane,</hi> who lay to the charge of the Elect People of God, called <hi>Quakers, That they deny the Bloud of Chriſt, and his Body, and Reſurrection, and that they deny the Lord that bought them, and trample the Blood of the Covenant under their feet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the great Out-cry in the Mouthes of ſuch as know not what they ſay, nor whereof they affirm, lifting up their Voices (like the unbelieving Jews) of Hereſie and Blaſphemy againſt us; and all this is becauſe we anſwer not their Wils, and the Imaginations of their dark mind, but according to the Manifeſtation of God in every mans Conſcience (as the true Apoſtles and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt did) and according to the Scriptures of Truth, which Holy Men of God ſpake forth, as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt; as will plainly appear to all whoſe Eye the Lord hath opened; which may give much ſatisfaction to ſuch as ſincerely deſire to know the Truth (as it is in Jeſus) and walk in it, for whoſe ſake and the Vindication of the Truth and People of God, is this written,</p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM BAYLY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1667.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:42619:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42619:2"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>READER, (who ever thou art) conſider ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly that the things of God and the true knowledge of them are of deep and weighty concernment, and there are but few (in compariſon) that have attained to the true and right knowledge of the Myſteries of his everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Kingdom; notwithſtanding their great noiſe and talk of Profeſſion, <hi>the things that truly belong to their peace are hid from their Eyes, and their Houſe is deſolate,</hi> and ſo will remain till they are turned from the Darkneſs, to the Light of Chriſt which ſhines in their hearts, as it is written: <hi>God who commanded Light to ſhine out of darkneſs, hath alſo ſhined in our hearts, to give us the light of the knowledge of the glory of God in the Face of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Mark here, what gives the true knowledge of the things of God (which the natural man underſtands not, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned) it is the Light which ſhines in the hearts of people, which is the Maifeſtation of the Spirit of God given to every man to profit withal; and except people be turned to this, and learn of it, they can never be profited in the Way, and Worſhip, and true
<pb facs="tcp:42619:3"/>Knowledge of God. Therefore while People are from th Gift of God in them, they put Light for Darkneſs, and Darkneſs for Light. And ſo if thou wouldſt have a clear and right underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of theſe things, and be fully ſatisfied in thy own mind concerning them, thou muſt wait in the Light of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt for Counſel and Inſtruction; for no man can know the things of God, but by the Spirit of God, who giveth his Holy Spirit to them that rightly ask it of him, to which I ſhall leave thee, to be led into the right underſtanding hereof, that the things belonging to thy Souls peace may not be hid from thee.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="query_and_charge">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:42619:3"/>
            <head>The Firſt Query and Charge.</head>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>DO you Quakers own that Blood of Chriſt which was ſhed without the Gates of</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>upon the Croſs, which when the Souldier thruſt in his Spear, forthwith there came Water and Blood; and they that ſaw it bare Record that this was viſible Blood, which came out of the ſide of the viſible Man Chriſt? Do you own Juſtification by this Blood, which was viſible, which we do believe you do not? For we could never hear you directly anſwer us to this matter, but evade it by other terms, and ſhuffle it off, not daring to ſhew your Faith and Principle in this particular; ſo that we conclude, and publiſh, that you are them that deny Juſtification alone by the viſible Blood, of the viſible Man Chriſt that was born of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin</hi> Mary. Thus ſaid Matthew Caffen.</p>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>As for the word [viſible] Blood, and [viſible] Man, which thou ſo much talkeſt of, (in this kind) they are terms quite beſide the Language of the Scriptures of Truth, or elſe I am very ignorant of ſuch Tranſlations: But we do as really own our Juſtification by the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt the onely begotten Son of God, as the Apoſtles and Saints of old did, (without any evaſion or ſhuffling) according to their very meaning, and plain Declaration; who ſaid, <hi>If we are in the Light, as he is in the Light, then have we fellowſhip one with another,</hi> (mark in what their fellowſhip was, Is yours in the Light?) <hi>and the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt his Son cleanſeth us from all ſin,</hi> 1 John 1.7. You may ſee here is nothing mentioned of the word [viſible.] And again, <hi>John</hi> 6.53. <hi>Then Jeſus ſaid unto them, Verily, verily, I ſay unto you, Except ye eat the Fleſh of the Son of Man, and drink his Blood, ye have no Life in you. Whoſo eateth my Fleſh, and drinketh my Blood, hath Eternal Life, and I will raiſe him up at the laſt day. For my Fleſh is meat indeed, and my Blood is drink indeed. He that eateth my Fleſh, and drinketh my Blood, dwelleth in me, and I in him, &amp;c.</hi> Theſe words of Truth we own, and witneſs; but your
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42619:4"/>word [viſible] Fleſh, and [viſible] Blood, which you would ſtrain us up to expreſs, to anſwer your wills, and dark imaginations, we do not read from Chriſt, nor his Apoſtles in all the Scriptures. So we deſire all People to take notice of the ground theſe People have to ſay we deny the Blood of Chriſt; for becauſe I did not anſwer <hi>Matthew Caffen,</hi> (in a late Diſcourſe about theſe things) in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs tearm [viſible,] (it being not according to the form of ſound words) he therefrom concluded that we deny the Blood of Chriſt, that we do not own juſtification by it; who might as well conclude the ſame of <hi>Paul,</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles and Miniſters of Chriſt, as of us, for not uſing the word [viſible] when they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the Fleſh and Blood of Chriſt; yea, of Chriſt himſelf, who leaves out that expreſſion which they ſo much contend about; and on the contrary, ſaith, <hi>The Fleſh profits nothing, its the Spirit gives Life,</hi> John 6.62, 63. Then tell me, O ye Profeſſors (of Chriſt's and his Apoſtles words) who ſay they are your Rule, What is that Fleſh that is meat indeed? And what is that Fleſh that profits no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, ſeeing both are the words of Truth?</p>
               <p>And again, take the words of <hi>Peter,</hi> (a Miniſter of the Word which endureth for ever) to the Elect that were ſcattered through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſeveral Places, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18. <hi>Foraſmuch as ye know that ye are not redeemed with corruptible things (as Silver and Gold) from your vain converſation received by tradition from your Fathers; but with the precious Blood of Chriſt, as of a Lamb without blemiſh, and without ſpot.</hi> Why do you not here find fault with <hi>Peter</hi> for not uſing the word [viſible] inſtead of [precious?] which was my term ſeveral times to thee and thy Companions in that Diſcourſe, which ye would not receive as ſatisfactory to you; ſo ye may as well be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied, and contend with <hi>Peter,</hi> and Chriſt, and <hi>Paul,</hi> and the Scriptures of Truth throughout, as with us about the word [viſible,] and call them Sophiſters, and Blaſphemers, as thou <hi>M. C.</hi> calledſt me, when I ſpake their words, without adding or diminiſhing, as may appear hereafter.</p>
               <p>And again, ſee the Teſtimony of <hi>John,</hi> a Servant of God, who bare record of the Word of God, and of the Teſtimony of Jeſus Chriſt, and of all things that he ſaw, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.1, 2. and in chap. 7. verſ. 14. <hi>And he ſaid unto me, theſe are they that came out of great Tribulation, and have waſhed their Robes, and made them white in the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42619:4"/>Blood of the Lamb;</hi> he doth not ſay in the [viſible] Blood of the Lamb, they have waſhed their Robes. So though you thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim againſt us in theſe things, and brand us with Hereſie, &amp;c. yet we have (and do ſee, whoſe eyes the Lord hath opened) more for us, then are, or ever ſhall be againſt us; for we have the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, and of all his faithfull Servants and Miniſters, and the Teſtimony of his own Son on our ſide; and if ye had under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood their Words and Writings (which ye ſo much talk of) ye would eaſily underſtand our Faith and Principles concerning theſe Matters; but as Chriſt ſaid in thoſe dayes concerning the zealous outſide Profeſſors, ſo ſay I now, <hi>I thank thee O Father, Lord of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, that thou haſt hid theſe things from the Wiſe and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of the World, and haſt revealed them to Babes,</hi> &amp;c. And much more might be ſpoken as to this particular of the Blood of Chriſt, but in the mouthes of two or three Witneſſes let theſe things be eſtabliſhed: which when people come to underſtand aright with a ſpiritual diſcerning, they will not cry out againſt us, that we deny the Blood of Chriſt, and trample the Blood of the Covenant un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our feet, as theſe men have done through their ignorance, the Lord give them Repentance, and forgive them, for they know not what they do: for the Blood of the Covenant is that which ſanctifieth, and <hi>without holineſs</hi> (or ſanctification) <hi>no man ſhall ſee the Lord;</hi> and this we do not trample on, or count an unholy thing, but do praiſe the Lord (that bought us) that we are made witneſſes of it, and do acknowledge our Salvation, as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Silvanus,</hi> and <hi>Timotheus</hi> did, (to the Church of the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> in God our Father, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.13.) to be <hi>through the Sanctification of the Spirit, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the Truth.</hi> Thus were they choſen from the beginning to Salvation, as ye may read: And theſe thing we do not count unholy, but do prize and eſteem them more then all the viſible periſhing things in the whole World, though you have thus belyed and reproached us.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="query_and_charge">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:42619:5"/>
            <head>The ſecond Query and Charge.</head>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t do you own Salvation by the Man Chriſt, that was born of the Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>and that was baptized of</hi> John <hi>in</hi> Jordan, <hi>and that preached in the World, and was crucified, dead and buried, and roſe again the third day, and aſcended into Heaven, and there ſitteth at the Right-hand of God, and ſhall come again to judge the World?</hi> (now mark, <q rend="margQuotes">If we ſpeak the Truth in the uprightneſs of our hearts, and ſay yea, to all this, it doth not at all ſatisfie them) but they further proceed with terms beyond what is written:</q> 
               <hi>But do you believe in the [viſible] Man Chriſt, with fleſh and bones, which the People faſtned their eyes on, when he read in the Book of</hi> Iſaiah? <hi>So that Chriſt Jeſus was a [viſible] Man, with Fleſh and Bones, as he himſelf ſaid to</hi> Thomas, <hi>A Spirit hath not Fleſh and Bones, as ye ſee me have; ſo they did ſee him after he was riſen from the dead, and this was [viſible.] Do you</hi> Quakers <hi>own Salvation alone by this [viſible] Perſon Chriſt Jeſus? for we believe you do not, becauſe you preach up a Light within, and not the [viſible] Man Chriſt for Salvation, and ſo we publiſh you to be them that deny the Lord that bought them, and ſo are of Antichriſt, and falſe Prophets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was the ſum of <hi>Matthew Caffen</hi>'s Queſtion and Charge, in that late Diſcourſe againſt us, who makes it his work to revile the Truth, and them that do witneſs it revealed in the inward parts, where God doth require it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.6.</p>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>The former Part is here anſwered already, with a word of Truth; yea, and as to the latter part thereof, I have this to ſay, That we do not deny, but own and believe, that he was the Son of God, and the true Chriſt, and the Saviour of the World, that did appear to his Diſciples, and did eat and drink with them, and talk with them after he was riſen from the dead, who ſaid, <hi>A Spirit hath not Fleſh and Bones, as ye ſee [me] have;</hi> and all that is, or was ſpoken and written by the Prophets and Apoſtles of Chriſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning him, what he was, or what he did or ſaid, we do really believe, without any equivocating, (as ſome of you uſually charge
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42619:5"/>us with, and with reſervations; to which we may ſay, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>If our Goſpel be hid</hi> (or reſerved) <hi>it is hid to them that are loſt, whoſe minds the God of this World hath blinded, that do not believe, leſt the Light of the Glorious Goſpel of Chriſt</hi> (who is the Image of God) <hi>ſhould ſhine unto them;</hi> read 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> chap. 4. throughout, (you that talk againſt the Light within,) and underſtand what ye reade, and what ye are crying out againſt, it's no leſs than the Son of God, if you will believe <hi>Paul,</hi> who witneſſed the Son of God revealed in him; and Chriſt the Son of God, ſaid, <hi>I am the Light of the World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But as to your Charge, I ſay further, That we own Salvation by no other Chriſt then him the true Apoſtles preached, nor no other Goſpel or Name under Heaven, by which men ſhall be ſaved, but by Jeſus Chriſt, who is the ſame yeſterday to day, and for ever. And for the word <hi>[viſible]</hi> its yours, and not Chriſts, nor his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, nor mine; and ſo I leave it out, and keep to the Form of ſound words, as the Apoſtle exhorts, and not meddle with it, leſt I add to his words, and he reprove me; but he that took upon him the likeneſs of ſinful Fleſh, and the form of a Servant, and was found in faſhion as a Man, and made in the likeneſs of Men, being in the form of God, thought it not robery to be equal with God; this Chriſt Jeſus we own, and witneſs Salvation by, and by no other, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6, 7, 8. And though Chriſt Jeſus ſpoke at that time, and upon that occaſion, of his Fleſh and Bones, that they might believe that it was he that was riſen from the dead, whom the chief Prieſts, Scribes, Phariſees, and Elders had cauſed to be crucified, which before he had declared to them, and ſo upbraided them with their unbelief in that particular; yet we need not be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braided with unbelief by any, as you have done, ſaying, <hi>We deny the Reſurrection of the Body;</hi> but we do really believe that Chriſt is riſen from the dead, and entred into his Glory, according to the Scriptures, who ſaid to his Diſciples at the Supper, <hi>I will not drink henceforth of this fruit of the Vine, until that day when I drink it new with you in my Fathers Kingdom; and that after he was riſen from the dead, he would go before them into Galilee.</hi> So theſe things they did witneſs <hi>fullfilled,</hi> according as he had ſaid, <hi>Whoſe Cup of Bleſſing which they bleſſed, was it not the communion of the Blood of Chriſt? &amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. And did not his Blood clenſe them from all
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42619:6"/>Sin, as they walkt in the Light, in which their fellowſhip and communion was? 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.7. read with underſtanding in the Fear of the Lord. And ſo mark your great Argument, upon what occaſion he thus appeared and ſpoke; <hi>A Spirit hath not Fleſh and Bones, as ye ſee [me] have;</hi> Did he thus ſpeak that his Diſciples ſhould alway look after Fleſh and Bones to appear amongſt them, and to be with them, and comfort them for ever? Or did he not appear to them in another form? And laſt of all, did he not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to <hi>Paul</hi> (who was called <hi>Saul,</hi>) as to one born out of due time? And how did he appear to him, (mark) <hi>When it pleaſed God to reveal his Son in me,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But here may an Objection riſe, <hi>Did not</hi> Paul <hi>ſee that very Perſon, or Body, or [viſible] Chriſt that the reſt ſaw, even the [viſible] Fleſh and Bones that</hi> Thomas <hi>felt, the print of the Nails, and the hole of the Spear, after he was riſen from the dead?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Suppoſe he did, (for he ſhewed himſelf ſo to Witneſſes, and not unto all) yet <hi>Paul,</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles, and Chriſt, after that, did not talk ſo much of Fleſh and Bones, and not at all with the word [viſible] as you do; but on the contrary, as <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf ſaid, (after God had revealed his Son in him,) <hi>Henceforth know we no man after the Fleſh; yea, though we have known Chriſt after the Fleſh, yet now henceforth know we him ſo no more,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.16. (Mark) he ſpeaks as well in behalf of all them that ſo knew him, as of himſelf, though they had been witneſſes of his ſo appearing. Now if Chriſt ſhould ſo come and appear, as you ſay, with viſible Fleſh and Bones, or after the Fleſh, as you look for him, <hi>Paul</hi> would not know him, nor the reſt of the Apoſtles of Chriſt, who were Eye-witneſſes of his Majeſty and Glory: Would they do well then? Would not they deny the Lord that bought them then? For he ſaid, <hi>We know him [no more] henceforth,</hi> (though we have known him) <hi>after the Fleſh;</hi> and ſpeaks not ſo far outward, as your word [viſible.] Is <hi>Paul</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles of Chriſt of your Judgement, or of the <hi>Quakers;</hi> let Gods Witneſs in you all anſwer? Would ye receive ſuch into Fellowſhip with you, that do ſay as Chriſt did, <hi>The Fleſh profits nothing, its the Spirit gives Life?</hi> when they look ſo
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42619:6"/>much at his outward Perſon, or Fleſhly appearance in that Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. And if the Apoſtles and Chriſt do well to ſpeak after this manner, Why do ye then brand the harmleſs <hi>Quakers</hi> (ſo called) with Hereſie, who ſpeak and own the ſame things that they did, and not contrary? As you may read at large in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Truth, how they all preached, <hi>The Kingdom of God [within] and the word nigh [in] the heart, and in the mouth; and that none ſhold ſay in their hearts, Who ſhall aſcend up into Heaven to bring Chriſt down?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And God who commanded the Light to ſhine out of Darkneſs, hath ſhined [in] our hearts to give the Light of the Knowledge of the Glory of God in the Face of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. But we have this Treaſure [in] Earthen Veſſels, that the Excellency of the Power may be of God, and not of us, verſe 7. And ſaid <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 45.13. <hi>The Kings Daughter is all glorious within;</hi> And who is this King's Daughter, but they whom God is their Father, who ſaid, <hi>I will dwell in them, and walk in them; I will be their God, and they ſhall be my Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.16. And this is our Meſſage, <hi>That God is Light, and in him is no Darkneſs at all;</hi> and <hi>the Light within giveth the Knowledge of his Glory in the Face of Jeſus Chriſt; and this Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Treaſure is in Earthen Veſſels: And know ye not that Jeſus Chriſt is [in] you, except ye be Reprobates?</hi> 2 Cor. 13.5. And <hi>I have hid thy Word in my heart; and thy Word is a Light to my Feet, and a Lanthorn to my Paths,</hi> ſaid <hi>David;</hi> he did not ſay <hi>the Scripture,</hi> nor the <hi>viſible Fleſh and Bones</hi> was a Light to his Feet, but <hi>the Word in his Heart.</hi> And, <hi>in the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and God was the Word; in him was Life, and the Life is the Light of Men,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>David</hi> ſaid, <hi>The Lord is my Light, and my Salvation,</hi> Pſal. 27.1. And <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaid, <hi>The Lord ſhall be unto thee an Everlaſting Light,</hi> Iſa. 60.19. And ſaid the Apoſtle, <hi>Now the Lord is that Spirit;</hi> and <hi>where the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Lord is, there is Liberty;</hi> (that is, where he dwells and walks, as he ſaid) and <hi>there is one Lord, and his name one;</hi> and <hi>Jeſus is Lord, who ſaid, I am the Light of the World, he that followeth me ſhall not abide in Darkneſs, but ſhall have the Light of Life;</hi> and if they have it, it muſt be within them, or in them.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:42619:7"/>
               <p>And again, ſaid Chriſt (who is the true Light) <hi>Neither pray I for theſe alone, but for them alſo which ſhall believe on me, through the Truth, that they may all be one, as thou Father art in me, and I in thee, that they alſo may be one in us:</hi> (ſee how this comes to paſs) <hi>I in them, and thou in me, that they may be made perfect in one,</hi> &amp;c. Here is the Father and his Son in his People, as God ſaid, <hi>He would dwell in them;</hi> and as Chriſt ſaid, <hi>My Father and I will come and make our abode with him that keeps his ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</hi> And this is the Language of the Scriptures; and <hi>he that is with you ſhall be in you,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>the ſame Spirit that raiſed up Chriſt from the Dead ſhall alſo quicken your mortal Bodies:</hi> here they all preached the <hi>Light within</hi> and <hi>Chriſt within,</hi> if ye can underſtand, and <hi>God in his People.</hi> And manifold more might be inſtanced to prove their Principles and Doctrine whom you call Blaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers: but the World ſhall know, that our Teſtimony is True in the day at hand, as I told ſome of you, when ye ſo fiercely contended againſt, and ſpake evil of the things ye underſtand not.</p>
               <p>And when I ſpoke of Chriſt, who ſaid, <hi>Before Abraham was I am,</hi> and that <hi>all things were made by him and for him,</hi> &amp;c. ſaid one <hi>William Burnet,</hi> a Baptiſt-Teacher, <hi>There was nothing made by Chriſt;</hi> then ſaid I, By whom were all things made in the beginning? Said he, <hi>By the Word.</hi> Now let all People ſee the Darkneſs of theſe Men, whom their envy hath blinded that they cannot ſee the plain Scripture, how that Chriſt is called <hi>The Word of God, Rev.</hi> 19. and in divers places he is called the Word; And ſaid the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, By him were all things created, that are in Heaven, and that are in Earth, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and inviſible,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 1.16. So its no marvel they op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe us, and revile us about theſe things, when they belye the Apoſtle, and contradict his plain words, who are like the unbelieving Jews, that looked at the outward age of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Chriſt, when he ſaid to them, <hi>Before Abraham was I am;</hi> Is not this the true Chriſt that was before <hi>Abraham?</hi> Was not he with the Father glorified before the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan? Will ye deny theſe things ſo plainly recorded in the Scriptures of Truth? And is not Chriſt Jeſus the ſame yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42619:7"/>day, to day, and for ever? And did not <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> ſay, <hi>He that cometh after me is preferred before me, for he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>See here, Did not this Baptiſt-Teacher ſee farther then you Baptiſt-Teachers do now, who cries out, the [viſible] Fleſh and Bones is the Saviour? And farther than the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing Jews, who ſaid, <hi>Thou art not Fifty years old, and haſt thou ſeen Abraham?</hi> Whoſe anſwer ſerves for you all, <hi>[Before Abraham was, I am,] Then took they up Stones to caſt at him,</hi> John 8.59. (Can you read your Spirit?) For ye throw the hardeſt things that ye can ſcrable up againſt us about theſe things, except ye had the outward Power and Sword in your hands; then, I am ſure, ſome of you would puniſh the Blaſphemers (as ye call them) with a Priſon, or Death, (like as your Brethren have done, for) <hi>We have a Law, and by our Law he ought to die,</hi> ſaid the unbelieving Jews: And the Pope hath a Law to Burn Hereticks, that do not believe the Natural, Viſible, Corruptible Bread and Wine to be the Real, Natural, Subſtantial Body and Blood of Chriſt, and ſo the Saviour and Redeemer: And in <hi>New-England,</hi> the Zealous Profeſſors of the Letter, (the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlayers and Murtherers) have Laws againſt the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and call them <hi>A Curſed Sect,</hi> and you call them Blaſphemers; So that Chriſt's Words are fulfilled, <hi>Ye ſhall be hated of all Nations (or Opinions) for my Name-Sake,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>I am the Light of the World,</hi> and <hi>before Abraham was, I am.</hi> And <hi>Lodowick Muggleton</hi> he curſes them, and cries, They deny the Son to be a Perſon in the form of a Man, which ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed death, and is riſen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And calls them the <hi>Curſed Sect</hi> of <hi>Quakers:</hi> But all your Curſes and Revilings, Scandals, Lyes, and Reproaches, will turn back into your own Boſoms, and ſhall not come nigh the Dwelling of them whom the Lord hath bleſſed; for we do not deny the Perſon of Chriſt, nor the Blood of Chriſt, nor the Reſurrection of the Body, as we are falſly charged, but do own them all, in their Place and Office, according to the Scriptures of Truth; and we are one with the Saints and Apoſtles in the Primitive time,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42619:8"/>in all theſe things, and ſo are not a Sect, but Members of his Body, of his Fleſh, and of his Bones, as they were, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.30. But his Sayings are fulfilled, <hi>If they have called the Maſter of the Houſe</hi> Beelzebub, <hi>much more them of his Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold. If ye were of the World, the World would love his own, but becauſe I have choſen you out of the World, therefore the World hateth you.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="query_and_charge">
            <head>The third Query and Charge.</head>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t do you</hi> Quakers <hi>own and believe the Reſurrection of this Body, that this very Body that is viſible of Fleſh and Bones, which we now ſee and feel and handle; do you believe that this ſame Body ſhall riſe again,</hi> ſaid Matthew Caffen, and his Companion <hi>Burnet,</hi> (while they were handling one hand with the other) <hi>For we believe you do not, but deny the Reſurrection of this ſame viſible Body of Fleſh and Bones, as we have good ground to believe by your Books, in which we cannot find that you own the viſible Man Chriſt that is riſen and aſcended up into Heaven, and ſitteth at the Right-hand of God; nor the Reſurrection of this ſame viſible Body; if you do, or do not, ſay ay, or no,</hi> (ſaid M. C.) <hi>direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Queſtion?</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>As I told thee then (in that Diſcourſe upon the <hi>Heath</hi>) ſo I tell thee again, That the Man Chriſt, and his Reſurrection from the Dead, I own, according to the Scriptures, which thou ſaid was general, and nothing to the Queſtion: Then ſaid I, I own the Reſurrection of the Body as <hi>Paul</hi> did, and mentioned his words, <hi>It is ſown a Natural Body, it is raiſed a Spiritual Body; It is ſown in Weakneſs, it is raiſed in Power; And there is a Natural Body, and there is a Spiritual Body, &amp;c.</hi> And whereas you cry, the ſelf ſame viſible Body of Fleſh and Bones
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42619:8"/>you believe ſhall be raiſed, and this is your Faith and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple; I do not ſo read it (in your tearms) in all the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Truth, though ye alledge that ſaying in <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> chap. 37. (about the dry Bones) <hi>I will lay Sinews upon you, and will bring up Fleſh upon you, and cover you with Skin, and put breath in you, and ye ſhall live, and ye ſhall know that I am the Lord.</hi> Now look in the 11th Verſe, and ſee the Myſtery thereof, (if it be not above your reach, for you are very near the Earth, though ye talk ſo much of Heaven) whether it was not ſpoken only of the Reſtoration of the Jews out of their Captivated and dead ſtate, as the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>What ſhall the reviving</hi> (or returning) <hi>of them be, but life from the dead?</hi> Rom. 11.15. Conſider well what ye ſay, and whereof ye affirm, for the Light will make all things manifeſt, and the Fire muſt try your Works.</p>
               <p>And we have read that Fifteenth Chapter of the Firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> through, and find not your word [viſible] in it, from the one end to the other, which ſpeaks as much (or more) of the Reſurrection, as any place that I know of; But I find <hi>Paul</hi> (an Apoſtle of our Lord Jeſus) ſaying, <hi>Thou Fool,</hi> to ſuch as queried, <hi>how are the dead raiſed up? And with what Body do they come?</hi> But he doth not tell people (as you do,) that the ſame viſible Body of Fleſh and Bones ſhall be raiſed up; but ſays, <hi>Thou ſoweſt [not] that Body that ſhall be;</hi> and in the 50th verſe ſpeaks very plainly, which might be a full anſwer to your viſible Fleſh, and ſame Fleſh, and to your ſhame; <hi>Now this I ſay Brethren,</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>that Fleſh and Blood cannot inherit the Kingdom of God, neither doth corruption inherit incorruption:</hi> And in the 24th verſe ſaith, <hi>Awake to Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſin not; for ſome have not the Knowledge of God; I ſpeak this to your ſhame;</hi> which were ſuch as he called <hi>Fool,</hi> that queſtioned and imagined about the Reſurrection of the Body, and what manner of Body it ſhould be, before they were awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to Righteouſneſs, and left off ſinning, in which ſtate they could not diſcern the Lords Body, not the Reſurrection; for Sin is Darkneſs, and the Wages of it is Death; and what can you ſee in the Dark, and when ye are Dead? What knowledge of God have them that are in the Grave. Therefore I ſay Awake,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:42619:9"/>and let your Eyes be opened, and contend no longer againſt the Light within, for it is that <hi>which gives the knowledge of the Glory of God in the Face of Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> And ſuch as know <hi>the Power of his Reſurrection, being made conformable to his Death,</hi> have ſeen his Glory; <hi>To whom be Praiſe and Eternal Glory, and Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, who is the Immortal, Inviſible, the onely Wiſe God bleſſed forever, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And much more might be written as to manifeſt your Darkneſs and Ignorance in the things of God, and of the very Letter of the Scriptures; and ſo denying the Light (which ſhould give you a good Underſtanding) <hi>ye do err, not knowing the Scriptures, nor the Power of God,</hi> ſee <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.29. which was ſpoken concerning the Reſurrection.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:42619:9"/>
            <head>Poſt-ſcript.</head>
            <p>THe Key that opens the Myſteries of the Kingdom of God, is the Spirit of God, and without it no man can rightly underſtand (or judge of) them, or have any true ſight thereof; for the Natural man is blind, and ſo ſpeaks by imagination, not at all perceiving them, becauſe <hi>they are ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually diſcerned,</hi> as it is written 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> chap. 2. And ſo often it happeneth with ſuch to ſpeak evil of thoſe things they know not; but in what they know naturally, in thoſe things they corrupt themſelves, (mark, naturally) its an eaſie thing for any vain Man, or Hypocrite to talk or diſpute about a natural thing, as you may ſee how theſe Natural Profeſſors uſe the word [viſible] about the Body and Blood of Chriſt, which I do not find written in all the Scriptures of Truth, as to thoſe particulars. And ſo becauſe we do not ſpeak to anſwer their wills, contrary to the Scriptures, they are highly offended with us, as <hi>Matthew Caffen</hi> was with me, becauſe I ſaid <hi>God dwells in his People;</hi> and that <hi>Chriſt ſitteth at the Right-hand of God;</hi> but <hi>M. C.</hi> ſaid with a loud voice, <hi>My Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our that I own Salvation by, is that viſible Man Chriſt, that is aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded up into Heaven, and there ſitteth at the Right-hand of God, that viſible Man, with the ſame Fleſh and Bones which he took of the Virgin</hi> Mary. <hi>Which Heaven doſt thou mean,</hi> ſaid I to him? <hi>I mean,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>that viſible Heaven up there,</hi> (pointing over his head to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Sky) <hi>What, up there, where the Sun, Moon, and Sars are,</hi> ſaid I? <hi>Yea,</hi> ſaid M. C. <hi>this is my Faith and my Principle, I care not who knows it, though you Quakers hide yours, and will not deal plainly, but are aſhamed of what ye hold,</hi> &amp;c. (That is falſe) Then ſaid I, Did <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeak Truth, and honeſtly to the People, or did he mock them, and deal deceitfully with them, when he bid them <hi>ſeek the things that are above, where Chriſt fitteth at the Right-hand of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42619:10"/>God, &amp;c?</hi> Or did he ſpeak of impoſſibilities to them? For if he meant up there, where the viſible Sun, Moon, and Stars are, the viſible Heaven; How was it poſſible? Or wherein was it any way profitable for them to ſeek things up there? Or what things were they there to ſeek? O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> did ever any of them obey his Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to whom he thus ſpake? Did any of them clime up thither, and find Chriſt fitting there in a viſible ſingle Perſon, as <hi>M. C.</hi> ſaid he was there ſo? And what things are there to be ſought, as pertaining to Salvation, let the Witneſs of the living God in all People that have but the leaſt underſtanding judge and anſwer? And whether theſe men in their imaginations have not made to themſelves the likeneſs of things in Heaven, or things in Earth, contrary to the command of God? For Chriſt doth not always ſit where he is, though he mentioned ſitting, ſignifying a place of abode; but <hi>Stephen ſaw Heaven open, and Jeſus [ſtanding] at the Right-hand of God,</hi> when he was before the Council, bearing a Teſtimony, <hi>That the Moſt-High dwelleth not in Temples made with Hands,</hi> as ſaith the Prophet; <hi>Heaven is my Throne, and Earth is my Foot-ſtool; What Houſe will ye build me, ſaith the Lord? Or what is the Place of my Reſt? Hath not my Hands made all theſe things? Acts</hi> 7.48. But <hi>Stephen</hi> was full of the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>looking up ſtedfaſtly [into] Heaven, and ſaw the Glory of God, and Jeſus ſtanding on the Right-hand of God,</hi> which they that gnaſhed with their Teeth on him did not ſee, <hi>for they did alwayes reſiſt the Holy Ghoſt (as their Fathers did) and they ſtopt their Ears, and ran upon him with one accord,</hi> as all the Profeſſors in <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> (ſo called) have done againſt the harmleſs People of God in this Age; ſuch as reſiſt that which is Holy in themſelves, muſt needs reſiſt, and reproach, and perſecute them that are filled with it, and born of it, and ſo the Scripture is fulfilled, <hi>they hated me before they hated you,</hi> John 15.18.</p>
            <p>And ſo though men may be wiſe, and zealous, and learned, and prudent, and great, and rich, and mighty, and be Rulers, and Teachers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet if they reſiſt the Holy Ghoſt (or Spirit of Truth) the Myſteries of God, and of his Kingdom are ſtill hid from them; though they profeſs and talk of them with their mouth and lips, yet their fooliſh heart is ſtill darkened, becauſe they like not to retain [God] in their knowledge, but like to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42619:10"/>retain only a kind of outſide knowledge of thoſe things that his Children do witneſs the Life and Power of within, and ſo they are [inwardly] ravened from that which only can give the true and ſaving knowledge of God, and of his Glory, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6.</p>
            <p>And ſo from the Wiſe (and Prudent of the World) in that which is natural, and viſible, God hath hid, and doth hide the Myſteries of his Heavenly Kingdom and Dominion, but doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal and ſhew them plainly to <hi>Babes,</hi> whom he <hi>forbids to caſt their Pearls before Swine,</hi> (ſuch as feed upon the Husk) <hi>leſt they trample them under their feet,</hi> and <hi>turn again and rent them;</hi> yet are we rent with divers and manifold Reproaches and Perſecutions, by ſuch as pretend themſelves the Sheep of Chriſt, and People of God, <hi>But by their Fruits ye ſhall know them;</hi> and eſpecially from the Teachers of the Letter of all ſorts do we meet with much oppoſition, but <hi>(Bleſſed be the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt)</hi> their ſtrength is but a Reed of <hi>Egypt,</hi> (where Death and Darkneſs is, which may be felt) and the Lord is <hi>drying up the Tongue of the</hi> Egyptian <hi>Sea, and he will make the Rivers Iſlands, and dry up all their Pools; And this ſhall be the Plague of</hi> Egypt, <hi>and of all the Heathen that will not come up to</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>to worſhip the King the Lord of Hoſts, even upon them ſhall be no rain,</hi> Zech. 14. (<hi>And the true</hi> Worſhippers are ſuch <hi>as worſhip the Father in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and in the Truth,</hi>) he that hath an Ear to hear, let him hear. <hi>And the Lord is making Wayes in the Wilderneſs, and Rivers in the Deſart, and the Wilderneſs ſhall ſing for joy, and the Deſart ſhall bloſſom as a Roſe, and grow as the Lilly;</hi> and this is the Lords doing by his own Arm, <hi>that no Fleſh ſhould glory in his Preſence, who is confounding the Wiſdom of the Wiſe, and bringing the Underſtanding of the Prudent to nothing,</hi> ſo that <hi>Babes</hi> and <hi>Sucklings</hi> ſhall ſay, <hi>Where is the Wiſe? Where is the Scribe? Where is the Diſputer? Where is he that can count the Towers? Hath not God made Fooliſh the Wiſdom of this World? the World by all their Wiſdom know no God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I thank thee O Father, Lord of Heaven and Earth, becauſe thou haſt hid theſe things from the Wiſe and Prudent, and haſt revealed them unto Babes; even ſo Father, for ſo it ſeemeth good in thy ſight, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.25.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:42619:11"/>
            <p>Theſe things I have written for the vindication of the Truth, and for the manifeſting the Darkneſs of them that reproach and oppoſe it, and them that live in it; and for their Souls ſake that have any true breathings, or ſincere deſires after the true Knowledge of the True and Living God; <hi>for to know thee the only true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent, is Life Eternal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> 1. Whether there be any more Saviours of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Soul but one, that is able to ſave it, or to bring Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to it, yea, or nay?</p>
            <p>If you ſay nay, there is but one able to ſave and able to deſtroy, as the Lord ſaid, <hi>Beſide me there is no Saviour, and there is no other Name under Heaven by which Men can be ſaved, but Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Then whether the [viſible] Perſon of Fleſh and Bones be the only Saviour, ſeeing the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>the Ingrafted Word is able to ſave the Soul; and the Grace of God that bringeth [Salvation] hath appeared to [all] Men;</hi> And who was <hi>Enoch</hi>'s Saviour, and the Prophets, who were before that viſible Fleſh and Bones was?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether the viſible Perſon of Fleſh and Bones be the [Ingrafted Word?] Or whether that Perſon hath appeared to [all Men,] ſeeing that which bringeth [Salvation] hath, I leave it to the Witneſs of God in you all to conſider and judge? For if you ſay the viſible man with viſible Fleſh and Bones is the alone Saviour, (as you have ſaid) Then whether this viſible man be in the hearts of People? for the Apoſtle preached Chriſt, <hi>[the Word] nigh in the Heart, and in the Mouth, and the [In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted Word] is able to ſave the Soul;</hi> ſo be did not preach a viſible Chriſt with Fleſh and Bones, as you do, but the Word, (which W. B. ſaid was not Chriſt.) And <hi>Paul</hi> preached <hi>God that made the World, &amp;c. that was not far from every one of us,</hi> (the Inviſible God;) but you preach a viſible man with Fleſh and Bones, at a great diſtance from all People, above, where the Sun, Moon, and Stars are, as <hi>M. C.</hi> ſaid his Saviour was, which he owned for Salvation. So let all People read with modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42619:11"/>and ſee how contrary theſe zealous Profeſſors are to the Apoſtles of Chriſt, who deſired <hi>to know Chriſt no more after the Fleſh.</hi> And Chriſt ſaid to ſuch, <hi>Ye worſhip ye know not what, God is a Spirit, and they that worſhip him muſt worſhip him in the Spirit and in the Truth;</hi> and God dwells and walks in his People according to his Promiſe, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And whether the Fleſh (which you call viſible) be not the <hi>Vail</hi> ſpoken of, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.20? And whether <hi>the Pot of Manna,</hi> and <hi>Aaron's Rod that Budded,</hi> and <hi>the Holieſt of all</hi> were not within the <hi>Vail?</hi> And whether that <hi>Vail</hi> in the old time, was not a Type of this <hi>Vail through which this New and Living Way is conſecrated for us?</hi> read <hi>Hebrews</hi> 10. and underſtand what ye read.</p>
            <p n="5">5. And whether ſuch as were made <hi>to ſit together in Heavenly Places in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> (who would know him no more after the Fleſh) were not come within the <hi>Vail,</hi> where the true Bread was <hi>which nouriſhes their Souls up unto Eternal Life,</hi> which the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na was a Type of?</p>
            <p n="6">6. And whether the Bodies of the Saints did not become <hi>the Temples of the Living God,</hi> and did not he <hi>dwell in them,</hi> and <hi>walk in them?</hi> And he that knew not Chriſt in him, was not he a Stranger to the New and Living Way, and a Reprobate? Or were the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Places in Chriſt, where they ſat above the Skyes?</p>
            <p n="7">7. And when <hi>Matthew Caffen</hi> ſaid his Saviour was up in the Heaven, where the Sun, Moon, and Stars are, which are viſible without him; Did he not then ask me where my God was that I worſhipped and ſerved? And did I not plainly tell him, (before many People;) <hi>that he dwelt in me, according to his Promiſe, and that he was my Saviour:</hi> And didſt not thee <hi>M. C.</hi> cry out with a loud voice, <hi>O Blaſphemy!</hi> (juſt like the Jews againſt Chriſt, and them that ſtopt their Ears againſt <hi>Stephen,</hi>) but did not I reply to thee, Then call the Scripture Blaſphemy; nay, thou may as well call the Lord Blaſphemer, for ſpeaking ſo, for they are his Words and Promiſe to his People? <hi>I will dwell in them, and walk in them; I will be their God, and they ſhall be my People.</hi> Here all may ſee the Darkneſs and Blindneſs that is happened to theſe men, who do withſtand the Truth of God, and his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Promiſes, as <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> withſtood <hi>Moſes,</hi> but
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42619:12"/>their folly will be made manifeſt to all men as theirs was, who call ſuch Blaſphemers who witneſs the Promiſe of the Father (which Chriſt bid his Diſciples wait for) fulfilled.</p>
            <div type="objection_and_answer">
               <p>But ſome may ſay, <hi>If God and Chriſt, and Juſtification, and Salvation, and all muſt be known within; Then, what Benefit have you by the Death and Sufferings of Chriſt? And for what end came he into the World? And what advantage have any People by theſe things?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Much every may; for firſt, he in his Birth and coming in the Fleſh, was the opening of a Door (though under a <hi>Vail</hi> to the Carnal Eye) to ſee into the Myſteries of his Kingdom, which was at hand, as he told them; as his being born of a Virgin, and then being carried into <hi>Egypt,</hi> and then being brought back again, as alſo his being kept out of the Inn, which was full of Gueſts in the dayes of Taxing; and his being wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſwadling clothes, and laid in a Manger, ſhewed his enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment in the World, and among the Profeſſors of all ſorts, that ſaw not the Inviſible Life, but lookt at the viſible appearance, and ſo <hi>his Face was more marr'd then any mans, and his form more then the ſons of men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And then in his Preaching, he told for what end he was born, and came into the World, <hi>to bear witneſs to the Truth;</hi> and ſo he fulfilled all the Types and Shadows, and Sacrifices under the Law, by <hi>his Offering once for all,</hi> and ended them for ever; and ſo <hi>a Body was prepared to do his Fathers Will,</hi> who would nor have any more ſuch Sacrifices and Offerings, but a <hi>New and Living Way muſt be conſecrated,</hi> for the People, <hi>through the Vail,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>his Fleſh,</hi> which was <hi>offered up once for all;</hi> ſo here all the outward Offerings (which were many, and often) ended; and now the Offering is in Righteouſneſs, in that which exceeds the Scribes and Phariſees, and the true Worſhip is now (as he ſaid) <hi>in the Spirit, and in the Truth.</hi> And ſo as they offered the Blood of Bulls and Goats, and ſuch like things, in their Sacrifices for Sin and Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion; ſo Chriſt at his Death and Suffering offered up a Body of Fleſh and Blood, which was prepared (as I ſaid) to that end, of his Father: So he did his Fathers Will, with which he was well
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:42619:12"/>pleaſed, ſaying, <hi>This is my beloved Son, hear ye him;</hi> ſo that God is in Chriſt reconciled; and out of him there is no Reconciliation, nor acceptable Sacrifice. And now all muſt hear him, who ſaid, <hi>I am the Way, the Truth, and the Life,</hi> and <hi>I am the Light of the World;</hi> belive in the Light, whoſe name is called <hi>The Word of God,</hi> which his Miniſters (in his ſtead) preached <hi>nigh, in the heart and in the mouth,</hi> and forbid ſaying <hi>who ſhall aſcend up into Heaven to bring him down,</hi> or <hi>deſcend to fetch him up, &amp;c.</hi> but the Word of Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they had, and this they preached, that People might come to Chriſt and be reconciled to God; and <hi>their Fellowſhip was with the Father, and with his Son Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>the Blood of Chriſt did clenſe them,</hi> and yet they deſire <hi>to know him no more after the Fleſh.</hi> But theſe things are Parables to the Wiſe men of the World; Therefore I may conclude as the Apoſtle did; <hi>Without controverſie great is the myſtery of Godlineſs, God was manifeſt in the Fleſh, juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in the Spirit, ſeen of Angels, preached unto the Gentiles, believed on in the World, received up into Glory,</hi> 1 Tim. 3.16. And ſo he is out of your ſight, who deny the <hi>Light within,</hi> for that <hi>gives the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his Glory in the Face of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as ye may read 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. and 6.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>THE END</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
